ORIGINAL STORY BY NATSU HYUUGA
（原作：日向夏）
THIS STORY IS A FICION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES ND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、组织名均为虚构）
MOREOVER, THE STORY HAS NO RELATION TO REAL-LIFE INCIDENTS AND EVENTS.
（与任何特定事件或现象无关）
How do you lower the price of a courtesan?
若是想降低娼妓身价的话 该怎么做？
If you get her pregnant, she is essentially worthless.
若是让她怀孕 就等于毫无身价了
Isn't that the restaurant you're going to?
您要去的店家不是那间吗？
All right. I'll be off then.
那么 小的告辞了
Here?
现在要走吗？
We're disguised. It would be pointless if I went in.
都特地乔装了 我再跟进去不好吧？
Right.
的确
I'll be off then.
告辞
I'm fine.
没关系
I think I was able to say that with no emotion.
我应该只是不带感情地说出事实而已
Enjoy the night.
愿您度过欢快良宵
A dream of my past? No, it was when I was a baby.
以前的梦？ 不对 是幼儿时期的梦吧
Is it because I talked about that yesterday
是因为说了那些话的关系吗？
Good morning.
早上好
Good morning, Old Man.
早上好 老爹
-What will you do today? -I have no plans.
-你今天有什么打算？ -没什么事
In that case, will you go to the Verdigris House for me?
没什么事的话 能帮我去一趟绿青馆吗？
Sure.
好
Hey, Maomao. Shouldn't you be at work?
早啊 猫猫 工作没关系吗？
I got the day off.
我获准休假嘛
You got the day off, but you still come to the apothecary?
明明休假 却还是来药房呢
It's on the way. It's not why I'm here, but…
顺道就来了 虽然也不尽然是那样…
Wait, Pairin!
站住 白铃！
We don't need to talk about that anymore!
那件事已经说够了吧？
Oh? Maomao!
哎呀 猫猫！
Welcome home!
欢迎回来
That's too hot, Big Sis Pairin.
很热耶 白铃姐姐
I'm cold from all of Granny's scolding!
我可是很心寒呢 被婆婆一直唠叨着
We're not done talking! Which will it be?
我还没说完呢 快说 你打算怎么办？
What?
什么啦？
I don't really get it, but Big Sis Pairin has it hard too.
虽然不太懂怎么了 但白铃姐姐好像也很辛苦呢
Just decide! It's your fault for not leaving this place.
还不快点决定 说到底 还不是你一直赖着不走
That's why I make these deals for you!
我才得主持这些事情
I didn't ask for that!
我又没有拜托你
-You're always so selfish! -What do you mean, selfish?
-婆婆总是擅作主张 -什么叫擅作主张啊？
What? Maomao is here?
什么？猫猫来了吗？
She was here the whole time.
刚刚就在了
Is she going to the outhouse?
她要去别馆吗？
Good morning.
早上好
I used to get kicked out because she hated me back then,
以前曾嫌弃过我 还把我赶了出去
but she doesn't have the energy for that anymore.
但现在已经没有这种气力了
Or, maybe she can't talk.
或是 已经连怎么说话都忘了
Her illness is progressing. Her memory has been ripped to shreds.
随着病情恶化 她连记忆也被撕裂得破碎不堪
Old Man's medicines work well,
老爹的药虽然很有效
but at this point, they're not effective.
但恶化至此 已经连安慰的效果都没有了
Even then, this is the only treatment we know.
即使如此 也只有这种治疗方法了
That customer is here again.
那位客人又来了
He's got a nose for this.
真是 鼻子还真灵啊
Call for Meimei.
去叫梅梅
The Verdigris House is now a prestigious brothel, but
虽然绿青馆现在是声名远播的青楼
a little over ten years ago,
在十几年前
there was a time when the name of this brothel was tainted.
也是有着并不光彩的时候
This courtesan took on customers in those few years,
这名娼妓就是在那几年间接客
and unfortunately contracted syphilis.
而不幸染上了梅毒
VERDIGRIS HOUSE
（绿青馆）
By the time Old Man visited the Verdigris House,
老爹来到绿青馆的时候
the disease had reached its incubation period.
病情似乎正好进入潜伏期
It could've been treated if he could inform them of the illness,
当时要是能告知病状 也许还能做好处理
but there was no way the women would believe
但对于突然出现 原本是宦官的男子
a former eunuch
所有人
who appeared out of nowhere.
都不可能无故地相信他吧
One has to take on clients to eat.
若不接客就没饭吃
That is the law of the brothel.
这是青楼的规矩
A few years ago, once the rashes reappeared again,
几年后 她的身体又再次起疹子
the tumor spread like wildfire.
肿瘤很快就扩散到全身
After that, this woman was forced to live in this outhouse
之后 女子就被关进这座别馆
where she cannot be reached by the customers.
放在客人目光不及之处
A courtesan who can no longer be of any use.
做不了生意的娼妓
At least she wasn't thrown out into the gutter.
没有被扔进水沟已经十分宽容了
The smell is trapped in here. I'll burn some incense.
味道都闷着了 来焚点香好了
-What's wrong? -Big Sis told me.
-怎么了？ -姐姐说
That weird glasses man is here.
那个戴眼镜的奇怪男子在店里
So you shouldn't come back here.
最好别回去
I see.
这样啊 我知道了
As long as I stay here, he won't come.
只要待在这儿 那个客人是不会过来的
A client of the Verdigris House. A familiar face of many years.
他是绿青馆的常客 也是有渊源的人
What a
愚蠢的
stupid woman…
女人…
Good work! That customer left.
辛苦了 那位客人回去了喔
Were you with him, Big Sis Meimei?
是梅梅姐姐在应付他吗？
There's no one else.
没有其他人了嘛
I'm glad. Big Sis seems to be doing well today.
太好了 大姐今天看起来很不错
Maomao, you got that offer again?
他又在提猫猫的那件事了
What?
什么？
Big Sis, how do you deal with them?
姐姐 真亏你应付得了他呢
It's not so bad.
是吗？
Granny doesn't say anything as long as he pays well.
只要愿意出钱 婆婆也不会多说什么
Grams wants me to become a courtesan for that very reason.
她想叫我当娼妓八成就是这个原因
If I hadn't been hired by the court, I might've been sold off by now.
要不是被雇用 恐怕早就被卖给他了
It's a once in a lifetime chance for some.
在其他人眼里 可是求之不得的好缘分呢
Don't you know how few courtesans desire
你知道能两厢情愿 又能如愿以偿的娼妓
and are desired in return?
有多么少吗？
Grams would kick away
老鸨的话 会用银两的重量
anything of that sort with the weight of the silver.
把那些想法都踢到一边吧
She's saving up for the ferry boarding fee for heaven.
她是在积累前往极乐世界的船资
It can't be helped.
没办法啦
I'm around the age where I have to start thinking of what's next.
我的年纪也差不多了 是该好好考虑了呢
She's not yet 30,
她还没到三十岁
but she's at the retirement age for courtesans.
但对娼妓来说 也是该引退的年纪了
You could work independently.
自立门户如何？
Just a little bit longer…
再一阵子吧
I want to work here for a little bit longer.
这份工作 我再做一阵子吧
I don't really understand
我不太明白
Big Sis Meimei's feelings..
梅梅姐姐的那份感情
I don't want to think about it too deeply,
但也不想去深究
if it's the thing called love.
如果那是被称作“恋慕”的感情
I left behind those feelings
那样的感情 一定是
inside the body of the woman who birthed me.
被留在生下我的女子胎内了吧
Should I rinse your back? It's been a while.
好久没帮你洗背了 要吗？
-No, it's fine. -Come on!
-不用啦 -别客气嘛
It's been a while since we rinsed each other!
洗背什么的 好怀念呢
Let her do it.
就让她洗吧
You probably can't come back again for a while.
明天之后 你又好一阵子不能回来了吧？
Really?
真的要吗？
We're offering you a service. Don't forget to bring more rich customers!
都帮你特别服务了 可别忘了贵客的事情喔
I didn't think the meeting place offered these types of services.
没想到相约的餐馆 竟然有提供花街那样的服务
I didn't go there to buy such things.
我明明不是去寻芳作乐的
Apothecary, may we talk?
药师 能说两句话吗？
Yes, sir.
好
Drink this with Suiren.
这个给你和水莲喝吧
It's a gift from the eccentric.
是怪人给的伴手礼
The eccentric?
怪人给的？
-Thank you. -Sure.
-谢谢 -嗯
I'll be going back to work now.
那我回去工作了
My, my.
哎呀
We're having a Buddhist meal today.
今天晚上要斋戒
So don't snack on any meat or fish, Xiaomao.
小猫也别碰肉或鱼之类的喔
Just because we're on a break
就算是在休息
doesn't mean you can wander off like that.
太过放松也不行喔
Yes.
是
A Buddhist meal.
斋戒 对吧？
Shoot.
糟了
I thought I'd be able to get my mind off of it once I started working.
我以为只要工作之后 就能把那些事情置之脑后了
Also,
还有
you're not allowed to hide strange herbs inside the closet.
也不能把奇怪的药草藏在库房里
She's really observant.
姜真是老的辣
If there's no place to put them, you could ask Sir Jinshi
要是没地方放 去拜托壬氏大人
to use one of the leftover rooms.
让你用空的房间怎么样？
No. I cannot use an aristocrat's room
不可 我不可以将贵人住的地方
as a medicine cabinet.
当做药柜来用
Xiaomao, you look like you don't care,
小猫看起来很大而化之
but you're actually careful about boundaries.
这种事还是区分得很清楚呢
I'm born of a very low status. It's very strange
我是出身卑微的姑娘
that I'm in a place like this.
能在这儿已是很不可思议的缘分了
That's true.
说得是
But just because someone was born into a high status
不过 即使是出身高贵
doesn't mean they're completely different people.
也别一开始就将对方当作异己
You don't know
世事会如何转变
what sorts of things life will throw at you.
人生会如何发展都难以预料
Dividing everything by status is such a waste.
只凭身分来区隔一切就太可惜了
You think so?
是吗？
Yes.
是啊
All right, time to work. Can you run an errand for me?
好了 该工作了 能请你帮忙跑个腿吗？
Excuse me! I'm here to get some medicine.
打扰了 我是来取药的
All right. Wait here.
好 稍等一下
It's nothing like the rear palace medical office run by the quack doctor.
跟后宫庸医管理的太医院 真是大不相同
This is close to the military base, so they treat many injuries.
这儿离军府很近 可能是因为伤者比较多吧
I love this smell that spreads a bitter taste in my mouth!
这个苦味在口中散开的气味
I wonder what's in the cabinets?
药柜里都装了些什么呢？
I want to raid this whole office…
真想把太医院翻了个遍
No, I can't! Stop it!
不行 要忍住！
What are you doing?
你在做什么？
She's from back then…
那时候的…
I'm just waiting for my medicine.
小的只是在等药罢了
Suirei!
翠苓
You were here?
你来了啊？
I'm here to stock up on medications for the station.
我来取哨站的常备药
I see.
知道了
The station?
哨站？
Right, we met before near the military base.
说起来 之前遇见她也是在军府附近
She must've smelled like medicinal herbs because she works at the military.
身上有药草的味道 是因为在军府工作的关系啊
Why does she hate me so much?
莫名其妙地被讨厌了呢
Do you need anything else?
还需要什么吗？
Not particularly.
没特别需要的了
She wouldn't need to work as a court lady in her position…
本来不用当什么女官的…
It's nothing. I'll get your medicine!
没什么 你要取药吧？
What medicine is this?
这是什么药啊？
Lick!
我舔
Potato powder?
薯粉？
This is for Sir Jinshi, right?
这是壬氏大人的药 没错吧？
Now that I think about it, there are many mysteries surrounding Sir Jinshi.
仔细想想 壬氏大人有很多神秘点
Like the work he receives regularly, about two times a month.
他似乎有半个月一次的固定差事
He takes a long bath the day before
他会在前一天慢慢入浴
and burns incense and goes out.
焚过香 然后再出门
Same with the Buddhist meals.
斋戒也是如此
Like a purification ceremony.
就像是祓濯仪式一样
Can eunuchs perform rituals as well?
宦官也能主持祭祀吗？
It wouldn't be strange if he was of royalty.
若是高贵之人 主持仪式也并不奇怪
But why would someone like that become a eunuch?
但要是如此 为何会当宦官呢？
Could it be that Sir Jinshi was also forced to be a eunuch
难道说 壬氏大人也是因为先皇太后…
by the previous Emperor's Wife?
因为女帝的独断 而成为宦官吗？
Like Old Man.
就像老爹一样
That girl's adoptive father is a former eunuch and physician.
那位姑娘的义父 原本好像是担任医官的宦官
If she was taught by a former physician,
若她是师承自前医官的话
it makes sense that she is so knowledgeable.
那有渊博的知识也说得通了
-But he was a former eunuch? -Yes.
-但他原本是宦官吗？ -对
I can't think of such a skilled physician who was a eunuch…
宦官之中 有过如此优秀的医官吗？
Excuse me.
打扰啦
Should we continue our discussion from last time?
要继续前几天的话题吗？
It seems you've done a terrible thing.
你似乎做过相当恶毒的事情啊
That is quite rude!
真是失礼
You're one to talk.
真不想被程咬金这么说啊
It took more than ten years to convince that old woman.
我花了十年以上 好不容易才说服了老鸨
So imagine my shock when someone snatched her away!
体谅一下我被横刀夺爱的心情吧
So you want your "treat" back?
要我还给你吗？
I'll pay whatever you want.
不 要多少钱我都会出的
I don't want to make the same mistake as last time.
我可不想重蹈覆辙
What if I say no?
若我拒绝呢？
In that case, I have nothing to say.
那样的话 我也无话可说啊
There are only a few people
能违逆大人的人
who can go against your word, with your high position.
比一只手的手指还少吧？
I knew it. He knows what my true identity is.
他果然察觉我的真实身分了
It all depends on what the girl thinks.
但是 “小女”又会怎么想呢？
I hate this.
真不快
So, that's how it is.
也就是这么一回事吧
I don't want to accept it.
虽然不想接受
But Lakan is Maomao's birth father.
罗汉是猫猫的亲生父亲
Will you tell her that I'll come to see her soon?
能否请你转告小女 我这几天会去见她？
Goodbye.
告辞
-Apothecary. -Yes, sir.
-药师 -是
There's an official who wants to meet with you.
有个官员说下次想见你一面
Who is it?
是哪位大人？
It's the eccentric I've mentioned before.
之前提过的怪人
His name is Lakan.
名字叫罗汉
I'll tell him you can't.
我会想办法回绝的
Thank you so much, sir.
谢谢您
I'll be going back to work now.
小的回去工作了
I've never seen her look like that.
那样的表情还是第一次见到
I'd prefer it if I didn't see that ever again.
真不想再看到了
So he knows, huh?
他果然发现了吗？
This smell… It's a field of medicinal herbs!
这个味道…是药圃！
Here, and here, and over there!
这边 这也是 还有那边！
You again?
怎么又是你？
Shoot. I look way too suspicious this time.
糟糕 我这样子怎么看都很可疑
Don't worry. I haven't taken anything yet.
请放心 我什么都还没采呢
The dirt on your hands.
你手上的土
Is it safe to assume that you were planning to take these herbs?
我可以当作你正要采吗？
You're not in any trouble.
我并没有要责问你
This field doesn't belong to anyone.
这个药圃不隶属任何官署
But the physicians know of this spot too.
但医官也知道这儿
You shouldn't come here much.
所以你最好少来这儿
Were you assigned to maintain this place?
你负责照料这块地吗？
Not really.
不尽然
I just grow what I want here.
只是人家允许我在这儿 种些喜欢的东西而已
She's selectively picking out the weeds.
她只挑了杂草拔掉
I heard them call her Suirei.
我记得她叫做翠苓
I'm one to talk,
虽然不好说别人
but she doesn't seem to be the energetic type.
但她看来也不是活力满溢的类型
What do you grow here?
你在种什么呢？
Resurrection medicine.
还魂药
You mean…?
那是什么？
A medicine that could bring the dead back to life.
能让已死之人复活的药
If something like that exists,
如果那种东西真的存在…
I want it more than anything!
我一定会想要的不得了！
I'm joking.
开个玩笑罢了
Joking…?
玩笑？
I heard you were an apothecary.
听说你是一名药师
Just how skilled are you?
不知道你有多少本事呢？
I'm not sure.
我也不清楚
In the near future,
虽然这话说得有点早
I'll plant some morning glories here.
但我会在这儿种朝颜
Goodbye.
再会
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集预告）
Next episode, "Chance, or Something More?"
下一集 《偶然或必然》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻译：杨易